百鬼丸は慣れない音のために手傷を負い
Hyakkimaru got injured
due to the sudden return of his hearing.
ミオという少女の世話になる
A girl named Mio took him in.
ミオは、戦で行き場をなくした子供たちと暮らしを立てていた
Mio lived with children who
had been orphaned in the war.
だが、百鬼丸が鬼神との戦いに出かけたその夜
But on the night Hyakkimaru went out
to fight a demon...
あんなの…あんなのってねぇよ…
I can't... I can't believe it.
ん？なんだ！
Huh, what's that?
あ…あにき！あにき！
Bro?
どうしたんだよ！
What happened?
坊やかい？ちょうどよかった 手を貸しておく…
Perfect, help me out here.
あにき！大丈夫か！？
Are you okay?
あにきの足が！
His leg!
やっぱり手負いじゃ無理があったのさ  鬼神に取られちまった
He shouldn't have fought with that injury.
The demon got it.
あにき！痛ぇのか？
Does it hurt?
…え？今の声…
Huh? That voice...
あぁ  足は取られたが声は取り戻したらしい
Yes, he lost his leg
but got his voice back.
あにきの…声…
Hyakkimaru's voice...?
Party is over
それでも踊りたかった
But I still wanna dance
眠れないくらい
I can't even sleep
情熱の火はいつしか　いつの日にか
Someday, one day my passion's fire will
はなから気付いている
From the beginning I knew
炎はいつか消える
One day the flames would die out
何も要らないはずだった
Hey, I thought I didn't need anything
なのにまだ I'm so serious
But even now, I'm so serious
ああ　まだ間に合う
Ah... I still have time to make it
ああ ただ Burn it up Baby
Ah... but I'm gonna burn it up, baby
Sorry darling そんなに甘くないよ
Sorry darling, it's not that easy
でもきっとそんなに悪くないよ
But surely it's not that bad either
ああ Give me fire!
Give me fire
Light it up Baby 燃やしちゃうぜ
Light it up, baby.
I'm gonna burn it up, yeah
Party is over
Sorry darling Hurry up
Ah... I still have time to make it
ああただBurn it up
Sorry darling Hurry up
Ah... I still have time to make it
Give me fire
Light it up Baby 燃やしちゃうぜ
Light it up, baby.
I'm gonna burn it up, yeah
#6 The story of the Moriko Song, part 2
ミオ姉！
Mio!
おかえり！
You're home.
ただいま！
Hi there.
Ow...
どうしたんだよ！ケガしてるじゃねぇか！
What did you do? You're hurt.
大したことないよ ちょっと転んじゃって…
It's nothing, I just tripped.
大丈夫か？早く休まねぇと…
Are you okay? You need to rest up.
やっぱり両方の陣で働くなんて無理なんだって
I told you that you shouldn't work
at both camps.
今までどおり…
Stop going...
それは!?
What's that?
あぁ…それがさぁ
Oh. Well, you see...
百鬼丸！
Hyakkimaru!
何があったの？
What happened?
命にゃ別状ないよ
It won't kill him.
ま、戦うには早すぎたのさ
It was just too early for him to fight.
ミオ姉…人のことはいいから早く寝ろって
Mio, never mind him. Get some sleep.
でも…私のほうが慣れてるから
It's okay, I'm used to this.
あんたはみんなの食事をね
You get food ready for everyone.
くそっ！
Dammit!
どうしたんだよ急に！兄貴のそばについてなくていいのか？
What, shouldn't you be
keeping watch over your guy?
あぁ
Yeah...
まぁ、ミオ姉がいれば安心だけどな
But Mio will take good care of him.
まったく…ミオ姉の世話好きにも困ったもんだよ
Jeez, Mio sure likes
to take care of people.
ひと晩じゅう働いて疲れてるってのに…
After working all night.
タケ  お前姉ちゃんが働いてるとこ見たことあるのか？
Take, have you ever seen
your sis at work?
俺はいつも留守番だ
I always stay home.
チビたちだけ残しとけねぇからな
Can't leave the little ones alone.
そうか…
Right.
しょうがねぇよ！今はミオ姉の稼ぎがなきゃみんな餓死するしかねぇんだ
I mean, we have to rely on her
or we'll all starve to death.
別に責めちゃいねぇよ
I'm not blaming you or anything.
俺たちさ、約束してんだよ  俺たちの田んぼを持つって
We all made a promise together
to someday own our own rice paddy.
田んぼ？
Rice paddy?
あぁ  夏は一面、ダーッと青くて 秋には黄金色になる田んぼだ
It's gonna be all green in the summer
and golden in the fall.
黄金色だぞ!?
Golden, you know?
それで米が食いきれねぇほど取れるんだ！
We'll grow more rice than we can eat.
俺たちは戦で丸焼けか 日照りでカラカラの田んぼしか見たことねぇけど
We've only seen rice paddies burnt by war
or dried up by droughts.
ミオ姉が子供の頃はそうだったって
But Mio said
they all used to be golden.
いつか…私たちの田んぼを持とうね
Let's make our very own rice paddy
some day.
青くて黄金色で、私たちだけの
Green and golden. And all ours.
もう少しすりゃあ、俺も働きに行けるし そしたらミオ姉に楽させてやるよ！
I'll be able to work too in a little bit,
so Mio won't have to work so hard.
おーい！タケちゃーん！
Hey, Take.
あぁ！今行く！
Coming.
大丈夫！
Don't worry.
戦でたくさんなくしたぶん、戦から取り戻すだけ
War took a lot from us,
so let's get it back.
ここらでひと雨来てもらわにゃ
We need a good rain.
まぁ、毎年必ず恵みの雨はあるからなぁ
Don't worry.
We're blessed by rains every year.
あ、ホレ  少し雲が出てきとるが…
See? There are clouds coming up.
お願いです、父上！
Please, Father.
私を酒井討伐の援軍にお加えください！
Let me join the army
to suppress the Sakai clan.
あのような小国、すぐに攻め落としてみせましょう！
I'll crush that little domain
like it's nothing.
戦を侮るな！
Never underestimate wars.
そのような気構えでは、まだまだ初陣は早い！鍛錬に励め
If that's how you think, it's too early
for you. Back to your training.
父上
-Father!
-Tahomaru.
多宝丸
母上
Mother.
母上 私を戦に出していただけるよう 母上からも父上にお口添えください！
Mother, please tell Father
to let me go to war.
父上がならぬとおっしゃったのでしょう
Your father just said no.
ならばわたくしが言おうと同じことです
Then no it is, no matter what I say.
父上はわかっておられぬのです！
Father doesn't understand!
出陣さえお許しいただければ
If only he'd let me go,
きっと母上にお喜びいただけるような武勲を上げてみせます！
I know I'd distinguish myself in battle
and make you proud.
武勲など…
Of all things...
私の武勲などいりませぬか
My feats wouldn't impress you?
そうではありませぬ
That's not what I mean.
いえ…母上はいつもそうです
No, you are always like that, Mother.
狩りでどれほどの獲物を仕留めようと 武術の腕を上げようと
No matter what prize I hunt down or
how great I am at martial arts,
母上はお喜びにならない
you never care.
わたくしはただ…
I just...
戦にまつわるものを好まぬのです
I do not like things to do with war.
好まぬのは戦ではなく、私でしょう
It is not war you do not like,
but me.
何をそのような！
How can you say that?
多宝丸！わが子を厭う母がどこにおりましょうや
Tahomaru, what mother
would not love her child?
兵庫！陸奥！早駆けじゃ 馬を引け！
Hyogo, Mutsu. I wish to go riding.
Bring the horses.
はっ
若！
Young Master!
言いたいことはわかっておる！少し子供じみていたな
You don't have to say it.
I was being a bit childish.
少し？
A bit?
御方様はお優しい  若にはいつも…いつも
Her lady is kind.
Especially to you, always.
一度言えばわかる！
I heard you already!
母上が私に冷たかったことなどない…しかし…
Mother has never been unkind to me.
Yet...
若、若！危のうございます！
Young Master, please, that is dangerous!
ケガをされては！
You shall get hurt!
兵庫、陸奥！若を！
Hyogo, Mutsu, help him down!
母上！見てください母上！
Mother, look at me!
-Please, Young Master!
-Do come down!
若！
Young Master!
若！何をされているのです
Please, you mustn't be up there!
聞こえているのですか！
Do you hear me?
母上には、何よりも強く想いを寄せるものがある
There is something else that
Mother cares for much more in this world.
決して口には出されぬが…何かを隠しておられる
She will never say it,
but she is hiding something.
いや…母上だけではない  父上も
Not just Mother.
It's the same for Father, too.
わたくしどもは、国ごと小さな礎ひとつの上に乗っていることを
You, I, this domain.
We all sit atop a small cornerstone.
お忘れなきようにと
Please do not forget that.
一体…お2人には何が
What can they be hiding?
百鬼丸！
Hyakkimaru!
まだ寝てなきゃ！
You must stay put.
行ったらダメよ 悔しいのはわかるけど 無茶をして死んでしまったら元も子もない
You mustn't go. I understand that
you're frustrated, but what if you die?
私もね、少し焦って無理しちゃって
I pushed myself too hard as well,
so I get it.
バカだね…
I'm so stupid.
稼ぐのは簡単じゃないってわかってたのに
I knew it wasn't easy to make money.
ダメダメ
No, no.
二度と侍なんかのために泣かないって決めたんだから 泣いたら負け
I'd already promised I'd never cry
because of a samurai ever again.
百鬼丸もね 無理して死んじゃったら負けよ
You too.
If you try too hard and die, you lose.
れより、声が出るようになったんでしょ？
Anyways, I heard you found your voice.
すごいじゃない！ちょっと喋ってみて
That's amazing. Try to say something.
うるさいってこと？自分の声が？
Is your voice too loud for you?
そんな…
Really.
すぐに慣れるわよ！
You'll get used to it.
どろろが言ってたよ？今のままじゃ 穴ぐらにこもった獣みたいだって
Dororo said you were like
a beast in a cave the way you are now.
そうだ！歌は？百鬼丸好きでしょ？
How about a song? You like songs, right?
赤い花つんで
Pick a red flower
私ね、泣きそうになったら歌うの
I sing whenever I feel sad.
泣く代わりに ね？
Instead of crying.
赤い花つんで
Pick a red flower
あの人にあげよ
To give to her
あの人の髪に
In her hair
この花さ…
I will put the flower
行くのかい？
You're leaving?
あぁ　あの姉さんの言うとおり 、焦らず行くよ
Yes, just like that girl says,
I'll take it slowly.
鬼神のいる道を迂回すりゃいいことさ どうせ急ぐ旅じゃない
I'll just go around the place
the monster is. I'm in no hurry anyway.
ただ、いくら百鬼丸にそれを説いたって無駄だろうねぇ
Although it'd be useless
to try and tell Hyakkimaru that.
どうして
Why's that?
赤ん坊がおもちゃを取られたら怒って取り戻すだろう？
If you take a toy from a baby,
it'll get mad and take it back.
それと同じなのさ
Same as that.
そのうえ、取られたモンが自分の身体とあっちゃねぇ
Especially since what they took
from him is his own body.
あの歌を聞いてるときは静まるようだが
He's calm when he's listening
to that song.
静まるって？
What do you mean?
百鬼丸が赤ん坊のときから持ってる鬼神の炎さ
The demon flames Hyakkimaru has had
since he was a baby.
身体を奪われたときの残り火… みたいなモンかもしれないがね
You could say they're the embers
left from when they took his body.
穴ぐらから出てきたモンが 鬼だったってことがならねぇようにしなよ？
You better hope the beast that comes out
of the cave isn't a monster.
じゃあな！
Bye now.
…白い花
...white flower
そんなに見られると…
Don't look at me so much.
百鬼丸って、人の魂が見えるんでしょ？魂の色が
You can see people's souls, right?
The colors of them.
私のは…あんまり見ないで
Please don't look at mine.
きっと…すごく汚れてる  すごく
It's probably filthy. Really filthy.
不思議…この手は嫌じゃない
How strange. I don't loathe these hands.
殿からの叱責じゃ！
Lord Daigo is angry.
では、兵糧は
So no provisions?
それは送るとある 援軍もな！
He'll send them. Reinforcements, too.
だが…それを待っていては恥じゃ！動くぞ！
But it would be an embarrassment to wait.
奇襲を仕掛ける！決して悟られるな！
We will plan a surprise attack.
Don't let them sense it.
酒井の間者にはよくよく用心するよう、申し伝えよ！
Tell everyone to be on the watch
for Sakai spies.
はっ！
Yes, sir!
仕事かい？
Going to work?
そっか…あんた、私の仕事…
Oh, you know what my job is...
おいら、わざと覗いたわけじゃ…！
I didn't look on purpose!
いいの  私は恥ずかしいとは思ってないから
It's okay, I'm not ashamed about it.
行きていくためだもの
It's to survive.
でも、あんたが近寄りたくないのもわかる
But I understand
if you want to keep your distance.
汚れ仕事だものね
It's not a nice job.
それにしても…あんたくらいの歳で、よく私の仕事がわかったね
But I'm amazed at how a boy your age
understood what my job was.
おいら、おっかちゃんとずっと旅してて  色々…
I traveled around with my mama a lot.
そんとき、どんなに腹が減っても おっかちゃんが絶対やらなかった仕事だから
And that's the only job Mama didn't do
no matter how hungry we got.
そう　偉いお母ちゃんね
What an admirable mama.
だけど…そうやって
But Mama...
おっかちゃんは死んじまった
That's how she died...
おっかちゃんは偉いけど、生きてる姉ちゃんも同じくらい偉ぇよ
Mama was admirable,
but so are you for staying alive.
偉ぇ！
You are, darn it!
戦でなくしたモン、戦から取り戻してやるんだろ？
You're gonna take back
what war took from you, right?
今度はぶん取ってやれ！田んぼも畑もぜーんぶ！
Then take it all!
Rice paddies, farms, everything!
うん  ありがとね
I will. Thanks.
あにき  メシ！
Here, eat up.
さぁ どんどん食べて精つけなよ！
Come on, it'll make you stronger.
片足取られたぐらい何だよ！
So what if you lost a leg?
声取り戻したんだから、黙ってねぇで喋んなよ！
You got your voice back,
so say something.
ほれほれ、食べなきゃ出る声も出ねぇからな？
Come on, you need to eat
if you want to use that voice.
水水！
Here, have some water.
わりぃわりぃ
Sorry.
なぁ…あにき…
Hey, Hyakkimaru?
鬼神なんかに負けねぇよな
You won't lose to it, will you?
あにきが鬼神なんかに、なるわけねぇよな！
You'll never become a monster, right?
あにき！そんなことよりどんどん食べてくれよ
Anyways, eat up now.
赤い花つんで
Pick a red flower
あの人にあげよ
To give to her
あの人…
In her...
Oh, wow!
That's so cool.
私は仕事行ってくるけど、百鬼丸を行かせちゃダメよ？
I'm going to work,
but don't let Hyakkimaru go to fight it.
まだ戦いなんて無理だから
His body isn't ready for it.
わかってるって
I know.
すげぇな！手に仕込んであるのか！
That's so cool. It's stuck on your arm?
でも！俺たちだっていいモン持ってるぜ！
But we've got something cool, too.
いくさ場で集めたんだ！
We found them at the battlefield.
ほら！これなんていいだろう！
Look, pretty nice, huh?
母ちゃん…
Mama...
あにきー！
Hyakkimaru!
こりゃひと雨来るぞぉ～！助かったぁ！
Seems like the rain's coming. Finally!
ミオ姉！大変だ！
Mio, we're in trouble!
百鬼丸が鬼神退治に行っちまった！
Hyakkimaru went to beat the monster!
どろろが追いかけてった！
Dororo went after him!
あにきー！
Hyakkimaru!
あ？なんじゃ！ぬか喜びかい！
That's it? Give me a break!
まったく…おいらに黙って行くなんてひでぇよ！
Jeez, how could you go without telling me?
姉ちゃんも心配してるぞ？
Mio is worried, too!
まぁ、足が戻ってよかったな
But good thing your leg grew back.
どうしたあにき…
What's wrong?
寺が！
The temple...!
残党がいないか確かめろ！
Check for any more survivors.
なんだよ…これ…
What the heck...?
どういうことだよ…
What's going on?
なんだお前 こいつらの仲間か！
Who are you? Are you one of them too?
この女は戦犯 わが陣にいかがわしい商売をしに来たが
This girl came to do lewd business
at our camp.
ゆうべ酒井の陣に入るのが目撃された
But we saw her enter the Sakai camp
last night.
密偵の疑いありとして早急に処分されたのじゃ
She's been disposed of
for being a suspected spy.
姉ちゃん！タケ！
Mio, Take!
離せバカヤロ！お前ら、なんで…なんで！
Let go, idiot! How could you...!
その取り乱しよう…やはり仲間か！
I see you're one of them, too.
なんだお前！
Who are you?
こいつの手！
His arms...
姉ちゃんしっかり！タケ！
Mio, wake up! Take!
赤い花つん…
Pick a red flower
姉ちゃん…
Mio...
あ…のひ…
To give to her
斬れぃ！斬れぇ！
Kill him!
なんだ!?
What the...
貴様ぁ！
You devil...!
あにき…
No, Hyakkimaru...
穴ぐらから出てきたモンが 鬼だったってことにならねぇようにしなよ？
You better hope the beast that comes out
of the cave isn't a monster.
た、助けてくれぇ…助けてくれぇ！頼む、助けてぇ
Spare me, please, I beg you...
やめろあにき！やめてくれ…
Stop it, Hyakkimaru, stop!
ダメだ！鬼になっちゃダメだ！
Don't! You can't turn into a monster!
頼む！頼むよあにき！
Please bro, come on!
あにき…姉ちゃんが持ってたんだ
Hyakkimaru, Mio had this with her.
種籾だ…
It's seed rice.
ちゃんと侍から取り戻したんだよ
She really got it back from the samurai.
田んぼを作る…ために…
To make her own rice paddy.
姉ちゃんは負けてねぇ
She didn't lose.
あにきも負けないでくれよ…
So you can't lose either.
頼むよ…
Please...
み…お…
Mi... o...
ほら
Here.
赤い花つんで
Pick a red flower
あの人にあげよ
To give to her
あの人の髪に
In her hair
この花さしてあげよ
I will put the flower
憂鬱が風に散らばり
Sorrow scatters in the wind,
吹き溜まって影になる
piling up to form shadows
僕らの足音は　無用を饒舌に諭す
Our footsteps admonish
indifference in such verbose ways
君の瞳の深さを覗き見て狼狽える
As I peek into your fathomless eyes,
I lose my composure
望みなどあったでしょうか　この行き先には
Is there any hope
in the place I am heading to?
戯けて笑うのは
I feign amusement and laugh
この道が暗いから
because this road is so dark
灯りを灯すのに　僕がいるでしょう
I will be there to shine the light
さよならごっこは慣れたもんさ
I'm used to playing at saying goodbye,
でも手を振ったら泣いちゃった
but I cried when I waved to you
僕らの真っ赤な悲しみが 暮れる 暮れる そして夜が来る
Our fiery woes fade... and fade...
until night falls upon us
当たり前にやってくる明日なら
If I knew tomorrow would be so mundane,
生きたいなんて言わなかった
I wouldn't have said that I wanted to live
よせばいいのに夢見てしまう 未来 未来 君のせいなんだ
I know it's futile but can't help dreaming
of a future... a future... you are to blame
"Arijigoku"